<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % version-entities SYSTEM "version.entities">
%version-entities;
<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>
<refentry id="gss-getting-started" revision="12 jan 2014">
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Getting Started</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo>GStreamer Streaming Server</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>Getting Started</refname>
<refpurpose>
Getting started with GStreamer Streaming Server.
</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsect1>
<title>Overview</title>

  <para>
    GStreamer Streaming Server (or GSS for short) is a custom HTTP
    server that has specific features that make it useful for serving
    media files, particularly live streaming video and video on demand.
    GSS works best as a specialized origin server for only the media
    portion of a web site.  This is similar to how you might use a
    separate web server (and different web server software) for static
    content vs. dynamic content.
  </para>

  <para>
    In this chapter, there are sections for installing GSS, configuring
    GSS, and a section each for using GSS for live streams and video on
    demand streams.
  </para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
<title>Installation</title>

  <para>
    The recommended installation method is to use the Ubuntu PPA
    to install to a server running Ubuntu.  This will install the
    appropriate files to start/stop the HTTP server when the machine
    is turned on/off, using Upstart.  When installing from source,
    the relevant files should be manually copied from the debian/
    directory in the source code.
  </para>

<refsect2>
<title>Installing Packages on Ubuntu</title>

<para>
  The GSS project maintainer occasionally uploads snapshots to the
  GStreamer Streaming Server PPA, hosted on Launchpad.  Launchpad
  automatically builds the package for precise on amd64 and i386,
  which can be installed on precise or any later Ubuntu system.
</para>

<para>
  The GSS PPA, including instructions for installing packages, can be
  found on Launchpad at
  <ulink role="online-location" url="https://launchpad.net/~dschleef/+archive/matterhorn-ppa/">https://launchpad.net/~dschleef/+archive/matterhorn-ppa/</ulink>.
  The package is called "gst-streaming-server".
</para>

</refsect2>

<refsect2>
<title>Installing from source on Linux or UNIX-like systems</title>

  <para>
    The source code for GSS is stored using git at 
    <ulink role="online-location" url="http://cgit.freedesktop.org/gstreamer/gst-streaming-server/">http://cgit.freedesktop.org/gstreamer/gst-streaming-server/</ulink>.
    No source code releases in tar form have been done yet.
  </para>

  <para>
    Code can be checked out from git using the commands:

    <literallayout>
      <userinput>git clone git://anongit.freedesktop.org/gstreamer/gst-streaming-server</userinput>
    </literallayout>
  </para>

  <!-- this has been borrowed from the glib docs -->
  <para>
    On UNIX, GStreamer Streaming Server uses the standard GNU build system,
    using <application>autoconf</application> for package
    configuration and resolving portability issues,
    <application>automake</application> for building makefiles
    that comply with the GNU Coding Standards, and
    <application>libtool</application> for building shared
    libraries on multiple platforms.  The normal sequence for
    compiling and installing GSS is thus:

    <literallayout>
      <userinput>./configure</userinput>
      <userinput>make</userinput>
      <userinput>make install</userinput>
    </literallayout>
    
    The GSS web server can be tested in development by running the
    program gss-streaming-server in the tools/ directory.
  </para>

  <para>
    The standard options provided by <application>GNU
    autoconf</application> may be passed to the
    <command>configure</command> script.  Please see the
    <application>autoconf</application> documentation or run
    <command>./configure --help</command> for information about
    the standard options.
  </para>

</refsect2>
</refsect1>

<refsect1>
<title>Using GSS for Live Streams</title>

  <para>
  </para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1>
<title>Using GSS for Video On Demand</title>

  <para>
    A collection of test files is available for testing video on
    demand.  It is at FIXME.
  </para>

  <para>
    Once the test collection is downloaded, untar the collection into
    a convenient temporary directory.  Then create a directory named 'vod'
    in the base directory for the web server.  If you are running in
    development, this will be the directory in which the gst-streaming-server
    resides.  If running from Ubuntu packages, this will be
    /var/lib/gst-streaming-server/.
  </para>

</refsect1>


</refentry>
